So you probably all know
this, but just to remind you,
the overall approach is simple.
You start out with a
training set of data
here together with descriptors,
which we use to derive a model.
Then we input the data,
and the model classifies it
based on some criterion.
Obviously, the devil
is in the details.
Based on this
high-level approach,
where do you see bias?
There's no bias here.
The algorithm-- say, a
convolutional neural network--
objectively analyzes
the data provided to it.
It's just math.
It is not just math.
We choose the training set.
We choose the algorithm.
Even if we think that
we are not biased,
we are subconsciously biased.
How do we actually
choose them if everything
is described by mathematics?
We don't really have a choice.
Duh.
The bias is already in the data
due to historical inequity.
You said it yourself.
So then our choice is
to note that and add
an appropriate loss function.
Does everybody know
what a loss function is?
Of course.
Yes.
Yeah.
A loss function is
just the error function
associated with an event,
such as facial recognition.
It is what should be
mathematically minimized.
Good.
Just to clarify, it
shouldn't be simply minimized
across the board but
targeted, for example,
so that the overall error
in facial recognition
is minimized with the
constraint that it is
equal among different groups.
But unless you have
equivalent training sets
for the different groups,
the statistical errors
won't be equivalent.
And you can't quantify
the errors in advance
to determine whether or not
they will be equivalent.
In other words, you can't choose
the loss function approach
to solve the problem because
the fluctuations or randomness.
The problem is statistics.
We have to have
a very large data
set to average out randomness
to acceptably small percentages
and make sure that our
data is representative.
Yes, but my point is that
it's just not possible.
I agree that we
could make the error
rates in facial
recognition algorithms
equal for Whites and Blacks
and for men and women.
But what about all the other
racial and ethnic minorities?
And for that matter, what about
all the different genders?
Even if we could
agree on what groups
need to have bias eliminated,
we can't practically
address them all.
Yeah, and that's not
even how the field works.
No one's going to spend five
or 10 years for each algorithm
to eliminate bias.
For cutting-edge
research, people just
try to hit 80%, sometimes 90%
accuracy for a given algorithm
and then publish a paper on it.
The incentives are such
that they can't spend years
getting 99% or so accuracy
across the board, at least
for new algorithms.
There just isn't enough data.
Better to just get
something out there,
even if it's not so good, so
you at least get credit for it.
If we could only
eliminate randomness,
our problems would be solved.
But randomness is good because
it's the basis of choice,
otherwise our minds would just
follow a deterministic path
based on our neural pathways
and electrical signals.
The heart of it is
quantum mechanics,
which introduces
intrinsic randomness.
Well, randomness doesn't
give you choice, just chaos.
That's also the
reason we have bias
to begin with, because of
random historical circumstances.
We want to eliminate bias,
not just make it random.
If it is random, then
maybe you will mitigate it
for minorities, or
maybe, at least for some,
you'll find a way to augment it.
[SCOFFS] That is what
I was saying, too.
So we seem to be stuck again.
Mathematics is the rigorous
way to understand the world,
but it doesn't give us choice.
In the world described
by mathematics,
choice is an illusion.
Professor, we ran
into the same impasse
when we had this discussion
last week during spring break.